taught the Quran,
created humanity,
˹and˺ taught them speech.
The sun and the moon ˹travel˺ with precision.
The stars and the trees bow down ˹in submission˺.
As for the sky, He raised it ˹high˺, and set the balance ˹of justice˺
so that you do not defraud the scales.
Weigh with justice, and do not give short measure.
He laid out the earth for all beings.
In it are fruit, palm trees with date stalks,
and grain with husks, and aromatic plants.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you ˹humans and jinn˺ both deny?
He created humankind from ˹sounding˺ clay like pottery,
and created jinn from a ˹smokeless˺ flame of fire.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
˹He is˺ Lord of the two easts and the two wests.
He merges the two bodies of ˹fresh and salt˺ water,
yet between them is a barrier they never cross.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
Out of both ˹waters˺ come forth pearls and coral.
To Him belong the ships with raised sails, sailing through the seas like mountains.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
Every being on earth is bound to perish.
Only your Lord Himself, full of Majesty and Honour, will remain ˹forever˺.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
All those in the heavens and the earth are dependent on Him. Day in and day out He has something to bring about.
We will soon attend to you ˹for judgment˺, O  two multitudes ˹of jinn and humans˺!
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
O  assembly of jinn and humans! If you can penetrate beyond the realms of the heavens and the earth, then do so. ˹But˺ you cannot do that without ˹Our˺ authority.
Flames of fire and ˹molten˺ copper will be sent against you, and you will not be able to defend one another.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
˹How horrible will it be˺ when the heavens will split apart, becoming rose-red like ˹burnt˺ oil!
On that Day there will be no need for any human or jinn to be asked about their sins.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
The wicked will be recognized by their appearance, then will be seized by ˹their˺ forelocks and feet.
˹They will be told,˺ “This is the Hell which the wicked denied.”
They will alternate between its flames and scalding water.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
And whoever is in awe of standing before their Lord will have two Gardens.
˹Both will be˺ with lush branches.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
In each ˹Garden˺ will be two flowing springs.
In each will be two types of every fruit.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
Those ˹believers˺ will recline on furnishings lined with rich brocade. And the fruit of both Gardens will hang within reach.
In both ˹Gardens˺ will be maidens of modest gaze, who no human or jinn has ever touched before.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
Those ˹maidens˺ will be ˹as elegant˺ as rubies and coral.
Is there any reward for goodness except goodness?
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
And below these two ˹Gardens˺ will be two others.
Both will be dark green.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
In each will be two gushing springs.
In both will be fruit, palm trees, and pomegranates.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
In all Gardens will be noble, pleasant mates.
˹They will be˺ maidens with gorgeous eyes, reserved in pavilions.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
No human or jinn has ever touched these ˹maidens˺ before.
All ˹believers˺ will be reclining on green cushions and splendid carpets.
Then which of your Lord’s favours will you both deny?
Blessed is the Name of your Lord, full of Majesty and Honour.